<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise declaryng [and] shewig dyuers causes take[n] out of the holy scriptur[es] of the sente[n]ces of holy faders [and] of the decrees of deuout emperours, that pyctures [and] other ymages which were wont to be worshypped, ar i[n] no wise to be suffred in the temples or churches of Christen men. By the whiche treatise the reder that is indifferent, shall se and perceyue, how good and godly a dede it was of the senatoures of Arge[n]tine, that of late daies they caused all the ymages with their auters to be cleane take[n] out of their churches. The authours of this litle treatise ar the ope[n] preachers of Argte[n]yne.</title>
            <title>Einigerlei Bild. English</title>
            <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13932</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103662</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839410</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839410</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3827</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13932)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3827)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 18:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise declaryng [and] shewig dyuers causes take[n] out of the holy scriptur[es] of the sente[n]ces of holy faders [and] of the decrees of deuout emperours, that pyctures [and] other ymages which were wont to be worshypped, ar i[n] no wise to be suffred in the temples or churches of Christen men. By the whiche treatise the reder that is indifferent, shall se and perceyue, how good and godly a dede it was of the senatoures of Arge[n]tine, that of late daies they caused all the ymages with their auters to be cleane take[n] out of their churches. The authours of this litle treatise ar the ope[n] preachers of Argte[n]yne.</title>
                  <title>Einigerlei Bild. English</title>
                  <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
                  <author>Bedrotus, Jacobus, d. 1541.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, William, fl. 1535.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Godfray for W. Marshall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1535?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC; W. Marshall appears in colophon.</note>
                  <note>Translated by William Marshall from the Latin translation by Jacobus Bedrote of Martin Bucer's Das einigerlei Bild.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: That ymages nor pictures ought to be worshipped.</note>
                  <note>Another edition, with added appendix, of STC 24238, published in 1535.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Leaf G4 torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Iconoclasm --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:1"/>
            <p>¶ A treatiſe declaryng &amp; ſhewi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dyuers cauſes take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the holy ſcripturꝭ / of the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of holy faders, &amp; of the decrees of deuout Emperours, that pyctures &amp; other ymages which were wont to be worſhypped / ar i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no wiſe to be ſuffred in the temples or chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſten men. By the whiche treatiſe the reder that is indifferent, ſhall ſe and perceyue, how good and godly a dede it was of the Senatou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of Arge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine, that of late daies they cauſed all the ymages with their auters to be cleane take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of their churches.</p>
            <p>¶ The authours of this litle treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ar the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preachers of Argte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yne.</p>
            <p>I dout nat but ſome popiſh doctor or peuiſh proctor wyl grunt at this trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe / but yet fyrſt rede and than iuge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:2"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ All the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of them which at Argentyne do preache &amp; teache Chriſte / vnto the good and godly reders do wyſſhe grace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ycauſe our moſte noble &amp; alſo moſt godlye Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours dyd right well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue &amp; ſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; manyfold euyls / which hytherto haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſtred by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon of pictures &amp; ymages / ar nat ſuffyciently taken away by the only exhortacions of prechers. And agayne dyd conſyder / that it was nat poſſyble for any man to decree or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde any thing con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge them more wyſely / than god had preſcrybed &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in his lawe and prophetes: They decreed / ordeined / and gaue forth a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that whatſoeuer pycture or ymages had ben wont
<pb facs="tcp:3827:3"/> to be worſhipped in holye places ſhulde both they and their aulters be clene take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away / &amp; auoyded out of ſyght.<note place="margin">Euery pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that my heuenlye father hath nat planted / ſhalbe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tirped &amp; plucked vp bi the roote. mat. 15</note> Bycauſe .iiii. yeres ago they had abrogated &amp; taken away priuate maſſes: And a yere ago foure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men and open maſſes / for fyrſte conſolatyon and delybera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of more pure ceremonyes to be brought in to their places.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">where ſhal Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers / cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons / no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mites / &amp; recluſes become?</note>Secondarily they lokyng for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne counſels and aſſembles / of whiche it was hoped / that ſome what ſhulde be decreed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the generall reformation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che. And thyrdly the wekeneſſe of certayne perſones / whiche coulde nat yet ſe / howe gret abuſyon / im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie &amp; wyckedneſſe is in maſſes / had ſaued the reſydewe of maſſes. &amp; they had ſuſpended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this condition / that if any man coulde proue by the ſcryptures / that they
<pb facs="tcp:3827:3"/> were nat contrary to Chriſte / they ſhuld be reſtored againe euerione. Moreouer ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be many men / whiche doo nat yet perceyue nor knowe / how moche theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges do hynder fayth &amp; trew godly lyuynge: we do eaſely coniecture that there be nat a fewe / whiche ſhall accompte this dede of oure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune wele / to be a folyſſhe and wycked preſumptyon. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / for as moch as it is the dutye of all chriſten men / as moch as in them lyeth / to gyue dilygence &amp; to prouyde / that the thynge whiche they haue godly done &amp; wrought / maye be accompted and knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of other men / to be none other wyſe than godly done. And alſo to take good hede / that no man may haue occaſyon worthely to ſpeke euyl of their goodneſſe (as Paule ſayth)</p>
            <p>Herfore we haue iudged it to be
<pb facs="tcp:3827:4"/> our parte and dutye which taught that the thynge oughte to be done which nowe our ſenate hath done in very dede / &amp; brought to paſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry dilygently to ſhew the cauſe of all this whole dede: but with as moche brefeneſſe as maye be / that if it wolde be / we might happely pacify &amp; appeſe the myndes / at the leſt wyſe of ſome perſones / whom this buſines hath troubled &amp; gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcontented / &amp; doubtleſſe / if we may optaine this one thyng (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is denyed to no man / be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo gret a malefactour) that we maye haue the one eare open to here what we ſhall ſaye: We feare nat / but that whoſoeuer can fynde in their hertes / and abyde to know theſe fewe thinges / which we ſhall allege fyrſt out of holy ſcriptures / ſecondarilye of the writynges of the fathers: And thyrdly of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees
<pb facs="tcp:3827:4"/> of emperours agaynſt pyctu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res and ymages. If it be ſhewed alſo of whom / &amp; for what cauſe &amp; conſyderation both they were firſt brought vp in the churches of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men / and alſo beyng defended haue contynued in the ſame. We doute nat (I ſaye) but that all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perſones / if it be ſo / that it be graunted vnto them to knowe the truthe / wyll alſo deſyre with vs / that this thynge whiche is done here with vs / all other churches of chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wold folowe &amp; execute in lyke maner. Therfore we pray and beſeche all thoſe / whoſoeuer ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat yet lyke nor a lowe this our exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple (which thinge it is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle thoughe it happen to many men / if a man conſydre which thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges haue euerywhere goten ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthe amonge Chriſten men) that they wyll voucheſafe to rede this
<pb facs="tcp:3827:5"/> ſhorte &amp; lytell treatyſe to the ende and entent / which fyrſt was made in oure maternall tongue / &amp; than by our moſte welbeloued brother Iames Bedrote / was tranſlated into Laten / and nowe at the laſte in to Englyſſhe. But let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſte before they begynne to rede / call for the ſpiryte of Chriſte / whiche onely ledeth into all veryte &amp; truth and that done / let them than gyue ſentence of vs:<note place="margin">Io. 16.</note> Chriſt the ſauyour of mankynde / graunte to all thoſe whiche bere his name / grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte and caſt awaye all ſuche thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / whiche do alyenate and call awaye the mynde from him / that they maye lyfte vp theire myndes vnto him / ſyttynge in heuen and worſhippe the father by him in ſpiryte and truth.<note place="margin">Io. 4.</note> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:5"/>
            <head>¶ That images nor pictures whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue ben wonte to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped ar nat to be ſuffred in the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of Chriſten men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit / there are verye mani iuſt cauſes which mighte ſuffycyently ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfy the myndes of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and perſwade them to take awaye images out of theire churches: yet no man wyll deny this cauſe to be without dout chefe and princypall / bycauſe it is forbydden in the fyrſte of goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes / that any maner of images ſhulde be had amonge his peple. For thus we rede in the ſcrypture:<note place="margin">Ex. 20</note> 
               <q>I am that euerlaſtyng god. I am thy god which haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegypt / the houſe of thraldom and bondage. Thou ſhalt haue no ſtraunge goddes in my ſyght. Thou ſhalt make vnto
<pb facs="tcp:3827:6"/> thy ſelfe no grauen or karuen ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / nor the ſymylytude of any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thinge which is aboue in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or beneth in the erth: nor of thoſe thynges whiche are in the waters vnder the erth. Thou ſhalte nat bowe thy ſelfe before them / nether worſhip them: for I am thy lorde god euerlaſtyng / ſtronge &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty / punyſſhinge the fautes of the fathers in the chyldren / euen vnto the thyrd generatyon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which do hate me. &amp; powringe forthe my goodnes / euen vnto the thouſanth generation of them which do loue me / and do obſerue &amp; kepe my com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes.</q> Lo / here are .ii. lawes of the lord ſet forth vnto the whiche nat withoute good cauſe amonge other / do chalenge vnto them ſelues the fyrſte place.<note place="margin">the fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement.</note> The fyrſt of them requyreth of vs / that we do take this eternall and euer
<pb facs="tcp:3827:6"/> beinge god (ſo as he is in very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) for our god.<note place="margin">The .ii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement.</note> The later doth nat only forbyd ſtraunge goddes / but alſo it forbyddeth bothe the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of them &amp; alſo of all other thynges / to be hadde amonge the people of god / vnto which people doutleſſe / that is to wytte vnto all true beleuers / all ſuch maner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes do appertayne. For theſe ar the trewe Iſraelyties / as it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the ſcryptures.<note place="margin">Rom 2 iiii.ix. Gala. 3 iiij. Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For Chriſt came nat to breke the lawe: but to fulfyll it fyrſt of any man. Nowe in veri dede they ar annexed to the lawe of god / &amp; alſo encloſed and conteyned in it / whatſoeuer thingꝭ do bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge any cauſe or occaſyon vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the loue of god or of the neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure / to ſhewe or put forth it ſelfe more and more.</p>
            <p>¶ In dede god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded very many thynges to his olde people
<pb facs="tcp:3827:7"/> whiche were greatly aueylable &amp; helpynge to the princypall poynte and ende of his lawe. But after that chriſt was ones exalted to the right hande of his father / and the holi ghoſt was ſent all abrode into the worlde / we ar delyuered &amp; free from a gret ꝑte of ſuch maner cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monyes of the law of Moſes.<note place="margin">Deu 7</note> As for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple it was goddꝭ wyl &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iues ſhuld lyue togyther by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues / abſtainyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; dealyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles (for he dyd nat yet vouchſafe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentyles ſhuld haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of his doctryne) to the entent no dout of it / <note place="margin">The ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyls wer nat than called to the faith</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld by ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be the more obedyent to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / by how moch they wer the leſſe corrupted &amp; infected with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the gentyles / wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge falſe goddꝭ.<note place="margin">As swal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge dyui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g two gardens or hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down maketh of tway<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne one / ſo dydde the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye of the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes deth makethe Iewes &amp; vs al one churche. <hi>Colo.</hi> 2</note> But after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heuy burden of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny rites &amp; ceremonyes of the Iues
<pb facs="tcp:3827:7"/> (which nat only deꝑted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other / but alſo made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enemys) was throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe. eph. 2 &amp; both the gentiles &amp; alſo the iues grewe togyther into one people. This lawe which forfe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelytꝭ / companye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyls could do no ſeruyce nor ꝓfet at all. Wherfore it was conuenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeyd lawe ſhuld be abrogated &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away. ſuch another lyke thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is circumciſion / &amp; alſo the rytes &amp; ceremonyes of purifycations / the choyſe of metes / the diuerſyteis of places &amp; perſones: &amp; whatſoeuer beſides theſe is red to haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded in the olde lawe / concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge outwarde ſacrifyces. For theſe thynges in as moche as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fayth nor charytie doth nowe requyre them: it ſhalbe lawfull &amp; free for vs either to obſerue &amp; kepe them / or els to leue them vndone. For the trewe honoure &amp; worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge
<pb facs="tcp:3827:8"/> of god / which hath ben by the preachynge of the apoſtels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly publyſſhed to the whole worlde / wyll in no wyſe ſuffre it ſelfe to be thruſte ſo narowly in to ſuche maner ſtreyghtes of places / dayes / meates / and perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Images ar forbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bi the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note>¶ But as concernynge ymages / the thyng is farre otherwyſe: For theſe beynge ones forbydden muſt nedes ſtande alwayes ſtyll forbyd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den / ſpecyally for this cauſe. By<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe the trewe honouryng of god can nat be / but either miniſſhed or els dyuerſe wayes letted: as ſone as we ſhall ſuffre the ſayde yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / contrary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god in churches / or in other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces / where they be honoured or els maye be honoured.<note place="margin">Faith is the moſt ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and ꝑfet ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of god. <hi>Ro.</hi> 4.</note> For ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall &amp; parfeyt fayth / &amp; the parfeyt honouryng of god / requyreth that we ſhulde do our dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:3827:8"/> this only god to be knowen in all places / that we ſhulde drede and honour him: that we ſhulde in all places and at all tymes with full mouth / prayſe &amp; magnify the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of him alone.<note place="margin">So may we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip non other but god alone. mat. 4. <hi>Deu.</hi> 6 10.</note> But ymages ar ſo farre from helpynge vnto thys thynge / that the ſame do dyuerſe wayes hyndre &amp; let euery man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the trewe honouryng of god. For who is he (I beſeche you) whom ymages ſet vp in churches / or in other more narowe places / haue nat rather made neglygent about the trewe honouryng of god / than holpen him any whyt to honoure god trewly. Ye / moreouer (if it be lawfull to ſpeke the truth) the true honour of god beynge ſubuerted and ouerthrowen / they haue quite blotted out of mennes myndes the remembrance of thoſe thynges / for whoſe cauſe it is fayned / that they
<pb facs="tcp:3827:9"/> were fyrſt ſet vp. &amp; though it be ſo that otherwhiles ꝑaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture by the occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe goodly gay admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nytours / ſome ſlypper thought &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſytory reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of god doth come ſodenly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our mynde:<note place="margin">Deade Images are but dombe teachers and can teach vs no lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ne yet fruteful knolege of god</note> yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thought is ſoner vanyſſhed a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>way / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it can gader ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rotes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the breſtes or myndꝭ of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for as it is but a thyng of mans de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſyng / &amp; receyued without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of god: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo was it neuer able to moue or ſtere our her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes &amp; myndes with the quicke &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely ꝑceyuyng / either of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefytes of god.<note place="margin">If the ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uely ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of god / do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th teache vs al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges by his wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de what is than lett to be taught vs by dombe Images</note> By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it hath come to paſſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no place hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> left to the lyuely admonition / which is by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatures of god: natw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe ſeyd creatures / bicauſe in all places we do ſe them &amp; handle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ought alſo in all places to ſtyre vp
<pb facs="tcp:3827:9"/> and renew in vs the remembrance of goddes infynyte goodneſſe. Breifly there is no cauſe / why we may more rightfully &amp; iuſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute (ſhal I ſay neglygence / or els our own conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt towardꝭ the true honor which is acceptable to god) vnto any other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge than vnto y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.<note place="margin">Images haue ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len awai goddes glorie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him &amp; taught vs to ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glecte &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne him.</note> For after that theſe began to be worſhipped i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certayne places forthwith flowed an vnmeſurable ſee of all euyls: for though we pas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouer / that god by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herof / was many ways greuouſly offended &amp; diſpleaſed / bicauſe the contrary to his open &amp; euydent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement nat only we haue worſhipped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but alſo puttyng our truſt in ſuche maner worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / haue ꝑſwaded vnto ourſelues / that herw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do wyn to ourſelues the fauor of god &amp; truſtyng vnto theſe vayne &amp; try<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flynge workꝭ / haue either vtterly
<pb facs="tcp:3827:10"/> nat mynded / or at the leſt wyſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue lothſomly &amp; diſdaynefully done thoſe workes / with which onely a chriſten mynde may be pleaſynge &amp; acceptable to god. and who is he but he knoweth that by the reaſon herof / very many men haue ben ſo tyckled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a meruelouſe vayne ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe / to gette of the lorde I wot nat what gret hepes &amp; treſures of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytꝭ: that if they had nat thought theſe maner tryfles to be moſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to god.<note place="margin">Pitho the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe of eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> No / nat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goddes Pitho herſelf / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all her ſwete elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence / ſhuld haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> able to haue brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in mynde / beyng ſlow ynough: yea / &amp; to moch vnto all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther workes of charyte beſydes / to haue pleaſure to laſſhe out ſo gret rycheſſe / partly vpon the makyng and partly vpon the payntynge / gyldynge / or otherwyſe garnyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge and deckynge of ymages.
<pb facs="tcp:3827:10"/> ¶ Beſydes all this I ſay (which is a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge more to be ſorowed for) this vayne honouryng of ymages hath engendred ſuch a confydence and truſt in a greate ſorte of men / <note place="margin">Images haue gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs a licentius libertie to all vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlines</note> that thoſe workes which ar in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede good &amp; godly / layde clene aſyde: they haue taken occaſyon to lyue a gret dele the more at lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and more lycencyouſly / bycauſe they ar perſwaded &amp; in ſtedfaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe / that with theſe workes they haue ſo gotten the fauour of god / that at all other ſynnes &amp; vycyouſe lyuynge / he doth wynke and wyll nat ſe them / &amp; as though hauynge lybertie graunted to ſynne vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed / they might gyue themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues at large to all maner vyces / e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they lyſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. If this thynge were nat well inough kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen vnto all men by experyence: we could proue it with ſuch many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb facs="tcp:3827:11"/> examples &amp; proufes / that euen he that were blynde ſhuld percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue playnly / that ther hath nat lygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely any other more perilouſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe cropen in to the churche / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this of honourynge ymages.</p>
            <p>Who is he tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doth nat here ſomewhat ſmell &amp; ꝑceyue the falſe wyly craftes of our olde enemye / <note place="margin">The craf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the diuel brought in Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to <abbr>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pue</abbr> god of his honour,</note> which hath neuer ceſſed to driue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde vnto ſuche madneſſe / that puttyng away the true honour of god / men ſhuld rereyue &amp; embrace this honour / which maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to go the cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god diſceyuyng all maner me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the vayne apparance &amp; outward ſight of ymages / as though (god wote) men by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of godly thingꝭ / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in very dede by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge els hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought in / but an innumerable hepe of all euyls. Moreouer / that man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:3827:11"/> heuen / erth / &amp; whatſoeuer is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in them / &amp; moſt ſpecyally man whiche is created to the ymage of god: fynally who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe / the worker of al theſe thingꝭ / doth nat wake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſtire vp to loue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; praiſe him:<note place="margin">Let the beholdi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uely crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures / in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goodnes of god ſo ſhineth &amp; is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cite &amp; ſtir thy mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to god / rather than the dombe ymages</note> No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / oules he be madder tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man of Bedlem / wyll beleue that this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wylbe moued gretly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deed &amp; vnſenſyble ymages / if ſo many workes of god / if ſo many creatures / no les ꝓfytable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelouſe / which ſet the goodneſſe of god before thyne eyes / can nat en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the / thou art doutles to vnſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble for to be admonyſſhed &amp; ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red euer of vnſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyble ymages.<note place="margin">For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he which is onely good had all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, he a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al to be good.</note> the goodnes of god ſhyneth &amp; apꝑith in all his creatures, There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but it expreſſeth god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe. All the world is full of thingꝭ whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che do nat ceſſe to put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our duty: that is to wyt / 
<pb facs="tcp:3827:12"/> that we ſhuld contynue to be vnto other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as god is vnto vs / &amp; that we ſhuld reſemble hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a certaine endles goodneſſe. But verily that this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hath the leſſe eaſely ben brought to paſſe hitherto / we may tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke images for a gret ꝑte therof for ſuche expenſes which ought to haue ben made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore nedy fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as beynge the very lyuely images of god / it was conuenyent to haue ſocoured &amp; made our fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des with our lyberalitie) we haue waſtfully beſtowed vpon ſtockes and ſtones. ye ſee therfore that the trew honour / &amp; that which only is accepted to god / hath ben by none other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo moch backed &amp; hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred as it hath by the vayne ſuꝑſtition of images: &amp; that the deuyl bi theſe craftes hath brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte of god / the ouerthrowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of faith / a more large lybertie to do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:3827:12"/> me lyſt vnpunyſſhed / falſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fydence in merytes / lothfulneſſe to exercyſe charite towardes our ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours: brefly an excedynge greate hepe of all maner euyls hathe ben brought in: &amp; to make an ende / a wyndowe opened to all maner vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; ſynne: which thinge although it might be eſely ꝓued by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples out of no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre:<note place="margin">
                  <p>For the worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping and ſufferi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preued.</p>
                  <p>And for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeng of yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wer ſome ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſo hyghlye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded</p>
               </note> yet at this <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent tyme let one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the kyngꝭ of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell ſuffyce. Fo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> howe many ſoeuer of theſe kyngꝭ thiſtorie of the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doth nombre amonge ſo many wicked &amp; vngodly ꝑſons / the ſame kyngꝭ it doth recorde to haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo idolaters &amp; worſhippers of ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges: on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde agayne / who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended for their loue and exercyſe of vertue &amp; godlynes they wolde gyue euydent teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye &amp; wytneſſe by diſtroyeng and rydding images ſhortly out of the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:13"/> way / that they were ruled by the holy ghoſte / &amp; coulde nat but hate all maner thynges whiche are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynable in the ſyght of god.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly worde of god haue ben brente, &amp; blynde y<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mages haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet vp in their ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / but now we truſt our bright bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to vs &amp; their bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhall be brent.</note>And as for that which ſome men do fayne that images ar the bokes of lay men (for ſo they ſay) it is nat only a weke reſon / but alſo a foliſh as who ſhuld ſaye that god / of all moſt wyſeſt / &amp; which is very wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom it ſelfe / either dyd nat knowe theſe bokes / or els through malyce dyd witholde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne people ſuch maner bokes &amp; monumentes / wherby they might be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance of godly thingꝭ. Forſoth it is a wycked thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ones to thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that god (which accordyng to his goodnes towardꝭ vs / lefte none of theſe thinges vnſhewed: &amp; as they ſay / poynted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his fynger which might helpe to further &amp; encreaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf / &amp; to ſtire vs vp
<pb facs="tcp:3827:13"/> alſo to the loue of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf. I can nat tell of what euyl wyl &amp; hatred had kepte this worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ymages fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne people. For nat only he dyd nat tech the worſhippynge of images / but alſo he dyd with ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; playne wordes vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bede it: as it apꝑith euydently by the firſt table of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law. Now what is more vnreſonable &amp; vnlykly tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if the vſe of images be ſo ꝓfytable as theſe men do fayne it to be / that god dyd nothing eſteme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſeing that in the meane ſeaſon he had be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gon to tech his people / beynge yet but yonge begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners / hauynge but ſmall knowlege w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one ſhuld en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce a chylde: Seyng alſo that he wold his workes &amp; benefytes to be openly knowen by ſo many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull myracles / &amp; by ſo manyfold ceremonyes. Beſydes this dyd en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb facs="tcp:3827:14"/> the people with holydayes<note place="margin">Holye daies mo than be neceſſary</note> / &amp; other rytes innumerable, Fynally he left nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g behinde to the ſhado<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wynge &amp; fyguryng of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vnto them. How fortuned it (I ſay) if images be ſo ꝓfytable that god for all this inſomoche dyd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng eſteme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde in no wiſe ſuffre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Sith than it is ſo / that it was nat lawfull for the people whiche was yet rude &amp; ignorant to haue a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny maner images / although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord dyd by many other dyuers ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyes by lytell &amp; lytell teche &amp; facyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame people. How moche leſſe ſhall it be laufull for vs / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (the truth now ſucceded &amp; folowed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of ſhadowes) hath now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de free from outward ceremonyes requyrynge none other honoure or ſeruyce of vs / than that whiche ſtandeth in ſpiryte and truth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:14"/>
            <p>¶ Let vs therfore haue ymages / nat of ſtone / nat of wood / nat gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen / or caſt in any moulde (al whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che god hath ones foreuer forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den / aſwell to vs as to the Iewes) But let vs rather conſyder the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye worde of god / let vs occupye and buſye oure ſelues in it bothe night and daye:<note place="margin">In the ſtede of Images let vs lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vpon goddes worde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Beſydes this / let all the whole frame of this worlde be a monumente and token to put vs in remembraunce of god / that whatſoeuer true godlyneſſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynynge in vs:<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> it may nat by the workes of men / but by the workes of god well &amp; after a godly facyon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered / enflame / and kyndle vs to the praiſynge &amp; louynge of him. ¶ Nowe as touchyng to this rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / that ſome men do make for to excuſe the vſe of images / bycauſe (as they ſay) after that god taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the nature of man vpon him / had
<pb facs="tcp:3827:15"/> vouchedſafe to lyue amonge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; to be nayled faſt to the croſſe / and wylled the knowlege of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf to be egally publyſſhed &amp; declared vnto all men: There is no cauſe why it ſhuld nat be lawfull to vſe images but yet moſt ſpecyally of chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifyed / to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might often tymes be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance / howe by his deth we haue gotten rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; ſaluation. Verily we do nat deny whatſoeuer holſom &amp; profyta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble thinge hath come to vs by the deth of Chriſt / which he ſuffrynge whan he was conuerſant amonge men / reconcyled ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde to his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther: yet that natwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge the ſame Chriſt dyd playnly wytneſſe that his bodily preſence was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge ꝓfytable.<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> It is the ſpiryte (ſayth he) that quyckeneth. it was therfore for our ꝓfyt / that he ſhuld bodily depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.<note place="margin">Io. 16,</note> And for that
<pb facs="tcp:3827:15"/> cauſe after his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vp into heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of his father / to the ende that he might cary vs alſo vp to the ſame place / if it be ſo that we haue ryſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with him in fayth.<note place="margin">2 Cor 5</note> Beſydes this / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paul / accordyng to the ſame ſentence doth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſay / that albeit we know Chriſt as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng his fleſſhe / yet now we knowe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo no more: he ſygnifyeth that another maner of worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge therfore is requyred of vs: that is to wyt / a ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all honour &amp; ſuche one / whiche may effectually &amp; ſtrongly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> hertes / which thinge ſyth it can nat be done by the benefyte &amp; helpe of images. let vs ſay adue &amp; farewel for euer to theſe triflyng &amp; vnꝓfitable helpes which ar rather hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derers of true fayth &amp; godly ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; tokens to put vs in remembrance of godly
<pb facs="tcp:3827:16"/> thinges. It is vndoutedly ſtarke madnes to deſyre to be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefytes of Chriſt by images / whan Chriſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf ought to worke the ſame in our myndes / whiche in vs &amp; all creatures wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all thingꝭ.<note place="margin">Lu. 22. 1 Cor 11</note> Dyd nat chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute &amp; leue vnto vs the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his body in his holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per / as a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t memoriall to put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his body cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed / &amp; his precyouſe blode ſhed for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption: ſayeng / how oft ſoeuer ye do this thinge / do it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of me / ſhewynge / pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng / &amp; gyuynge thankes for my deth vntyll I come agayne. And wherfore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue we inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted (as though we had forgote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goddꝭ own i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucion of his holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) of our owne folyſh fantaſtical braine an image of chriſt crucifyed to put vs in mynde of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / contrary to his
<pb facs="tcp:3827:16"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Let ds (I ſay) haue this Ieſus nailed faſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe ſet vp before the eyes of our mynd as often tymes as he tryeth vs / &amp; layeth his croſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs / by pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of trybulations &amp; aduerſytie. Let Chriſt ſo poſſeſſe &amp; fyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breſt of a chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath his na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / that there be nothyng but it do put hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his lorde / the creatour &amp; maker / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouernour &amp; the ſauyour &amp; preſeruer of all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Wherfore ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes as he loketh vp towardꝭ the ſkye / he can nat chuſe but reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſauyour Chriſt / which reygneth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue all heuens on the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of his father. Aſſone as he behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / by &amp; by he thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſt the ſon of rightwiſnes<note place="margin">Chriſt is the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes,</note> &amp; the lyght of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world / which with his beames lyghteneth his herte. whan he ſeith a man / he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth
<pb facs="tcp:3827:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> that Chriſt was made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for oure ſake.<note place="margin">Chriſt is man.</note> If he do mete w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a kyng or a prince / anon Chriſt the kyng of ki<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / &amp; lorde of lordꝭ is in his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hereth any preche or techer: Lo / ſtreight wayes hi mynde is vpon Chriſt the heuenly doctor &amp; maiſter:<note place="margin">Chriſt is our tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note> as the garment done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body / doth the body both ꝓfyte &amp; honeſty: euen ſo doth a godly mynde thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that chriſt is the very weddyng garment / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thoſe ꝑſons haue done on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues / how many ſoeuer haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed.<note place="margin">Chriſt is the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3 Chriſt is our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly meate &amp; drinke.</note> A chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer eteth &amp; drinketh / but forthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance that chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only &amp; the very meate / which fedeth &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſheth vs into eternall lyfe.<note place="margin">Chriſt is the foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne of lyfe. <hi>Iere.</hi> 2 104.7</note> If at any tyme he dothe occupye water / forthwith it cometh to his mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne / out of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we may drawe drinke agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:3827:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnſacyable thyrſt.<note place="margin">Chriſt is the lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be / the herdina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / the dore / the way &amp;c.</note> Brefly / ſo often tymes as he ſhall ſe / either a ſhepe or a ſhepherde / a gate / a waye / a vynetree / or a ſtone / forthwith he conceyueth an image &amp; ſimilytude of his lorde Chrriſt / <note place="margin">Io 1.10 14.15.</note> whiche wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly ſuffred hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe to be ſlayne and offered vp / for the reconſylya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the worlde / <note place="margin">Io. 10. Io. 14.</note> which boſteth him ſelfe to be a good ſhepherde / which is the waye and the yate / by which men go and entre into heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wytneſſeth him ſelfe to be the true vynetre / the corner ſtone / and ſet for a foundation:<note place="margin">Io. 15.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ</hi> 118. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28 1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 2 A goodly frutefull leſſon / a preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolation for the troubled mynde,</note> Fynally if thou be ſore vexed with aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytie / or els ſeeſt any other man to be in afflyctyon and calamytie. Beſydes this / if thou be troubled with paſſyons and noughty affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons and deſyres / forthewith (if ther be any percel of Chriſt in the) ſette before the eyes of thy mynde
<pb facs="tcp:3827:18"/> both the deth &amp; the reſurrection of Chriſt / <note place="margin">that the ſyck ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le go on pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vnto Chriſtes deth.</note> &amp; ſtedfaſtly &amp; depely conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / bi the meanes wherof thou maiſt in ſuch wiſe arme &amp; fence thi mynde with complete harneſſe / ſo ſure &amp; ſo full of moſt effettuall con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolacyons / that thou ſhalte be able eaſely to abyde &amp; ouercome what ſoeuer aduerſite ſhal fall vnto the. So that if after this maner &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon we wold haue luſt &amp; pleaſure to learne Chriſte perfytely in all thinges / &amp; his workes with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne lyuely felyng &amp; iugement of the mynde / which ſhuld tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſforme &amp; change vs: without dout the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of god ſhuld be meruelouſly au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gmented &amp; encreaſed in vs / &amp; we ſhulde alſo (as it were in a glaſſe) ſee / with what comelynes / &amp; after what maner and facyon the courſe of this lyfe oughte to be paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and brought to an ende / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:3827:18"/> no ymages canne euer be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to teache vs.<note place="margin">Eſ. 44.</note> For theſe (of what ſo euer maner they be) can nat ſette before thyne eyes any ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milytude of god / but rather with a vayne imagynation / whan thou weneſt that thou art warme with a certayne hote loue and deſyre to conſyder and thynke vpon godly thynges / ſodenly thys heate and feruentneſſe vanyſſheth a waye / and it ſhall make the more negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente to all true workes ſemelye for a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man / than euer thou waſt before. We do therefore py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſely deceyue our owne ſelues with this flieng deuotion / as they call it. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue thought our ſelues to be fed and full of bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter thynges:<note place="margin">winde is vayn do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctryne of men.</note> we fynde by expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence / ſooner than we wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> haue thoughte / that we haue ben fedde with mynde (as it is ſayde in the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:19"/> prouerbe) and that we ar emptye and voyde of meate / whiche doth nouryſſhe and make fatte in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and godly lyuynge.</p>
            <p>But as for theſe perſones whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che truſtynge and berynge theym ſelues bolde vpon the lawe of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten lybertye / do excuſe ymages / ſayenge: That for this cauſe they ar nat vnlawfull / bycauſe we may vſe them lawfully at our owne ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure / aſwell as we may other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde thynges / and therfore that it is better that there be images of Chriſte / than to haue ymages of prophane thynges.<note place="margin">The ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may nat be reke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge oute<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges.</note> I wolde that theſe men ſhulde fyrſt learne / that whatſoeuer ymages ar honoured or may be honoured / are nat to be accompted in the nombre of oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde thynges / and therfore they are vſed both to the iniurye of the diuyne maieſty / which only ought
<pb facs="tcp:3827:19"/> to be honoured / and alſo to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>befactacion and dekay of the faith There is no cauſe therfore / why the conſyderation of chriſten lyber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye / maye ſuffre in any wyſe ſuche maner images. For the lyberty of a chriſten man<note place="margin">The ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man.</note> is nat a lycence to do whatſoeuer he lyſt / but it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a voluntary execution of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe workes / which are done by the motyon of charitie / and nat by the commaundement and compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of the lawe.</p>
            <p>Nowe as touchynge the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſome men<note place="margin">The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections of ſome men.</note> / that there is no cauſe why it maye nat be lawfull for vs to vſe pictures &amp; ſtandynge images. For lykewiſe as men and thoſe perſons which haue ben ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycyentely inſtructed in the trewe doctryne and fayth of Chriſt / are nothynge offended nor do take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hurte by images: euen ſo weke
<pb facs="tcp:3827:20"/> perſons / &amp; ſuche as be nat yet well ſkylled i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> godly thingꝭ / eyther wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue better inſtruction / &amp; are taught the truthe / ſhalbe nothing hurt by the reaſon of images / or if they be ſturdy / &amp; ſuche as wyll nat be taughte / they ſhalbe nothynge the better / though al images were clene take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away. So than neither for the weke ꝑſons cauſe / neyther for their cauſe which ar perfect. it is neceſſary to take away images Doutleſſe / whoſoeuer with ſuche forked reaſons do coueyte to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende and mayntaygne ymages: They haue nat verye well conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered nor wayed the counſell and entent of Paule / whan he ſaythe:</p>
            <p>
               <q>All thynges are lawfull for me: But all thynges are nat expedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent nor profytable.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Co 10</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>All thynges are laufull to me: but all thynges do nat edifye.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:20"/>
            <p>And agayne in another place: <q>Knowlege maketh a man proude: but charytie dothe edifye.<note place="margin">1 Cor 8</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Alſo there is none that wyll vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande and ſeke god.<note place="margin">Pſ. 14.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And agayne: <q>take hede that your lybertye be nat an occaſyon of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and hurte to theym whiche are weake.<note place="margin">1 Cor 8</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>We do nat ſaye / but images may be hadde / but yet in no place to be worſhipped.<note place="margin">Solucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>We do graunt alſo that karuers &amp; paynters craftes / are craftes both gyuen by god / and alſo lawfull. But ſyth it is ſo / that in churches euerywhere / ymages are honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; namely Roodes. It is nat poſſyble / though thou prech neuer ſo ofte / or neuer ſo erneſtly vnto the people / that ymages are nat to be honoured: but that there wyl
<pb facs="tcp:3827:21"/> be ſome / which wyll holde on ſtyll to put of their cappes vnto them / or els to lowte and make curteſye to them: yea / to kyſſe their feete / to praye to them / to aſke of theym helthe / and to commytte their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and deſyres vnto them: For ſuche is the ſtrength of an olde ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted rotten cuſtome / and the deuyll agayne exercyſeth &amp; putteth forthe his craftes and diſceytes ſo buſely that they which be ones ſnarled in his bondes / wyll neuer refrayne from worſhippynge of ymages. Nowe bothe the occaſyons &amp; alſo the prouocatyons and entyſemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of all ſuche maner euyls / muſt nedes be taken a way / if Images were ones put down: And albeit truth it is / which they ſay comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / that where this vayne perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of images is nat plucked out of mennes myndes by the worde
<pb facs="tcp:3827:21"/> of god / there can nat the ſame be taken awaye: no / nat by the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge downe of ymages: yet is it nat generally true / ſo that we may thynke it to be trewly ſayde by all maner men indyfferently / aſmoch by one as by another. For by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men ye maye well and trewly ſaye the ſame / whiche contynue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes lyke to theym ſelues / and change nat their mynde / whether thou doſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wordes make playne the abhomynatyon of ymages / or els doſt in very dede ryd all yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges quyte oute of ſyght. But to them that are weke / and in whom there is remaynynge any / be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo lytell ſparke of godlye loue and reuerence: it ſhall nat be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable nor in vayne to wytnes and confyrme their doctryne with their dede: that is for to ſaye / after that thou haſt diſcrybed &amp; pai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted
<pb facs="tcp:3827:22"/> ymages ſo as they ought to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their owne colours / borowed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture / than dilygently to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde that the ſame alſo be ryd out of mennes ſyght. For by that dede weke men ſhalbe confermed / as in other thynges: ſo lykewyſe in this For thy teching ſhalbe al in vaine onleſſe the example of thy dede do forthwith folow / which ſhal cauſe thy doctryne to be of ſtrength and auctorite. Paule doutles thought it nat ſuffycyente that the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyans knewe an ydole or ymage to haue nothynge correſpondente thervnto:<note place="margin">1 Cor 8</note> But he wolde alſo that the ſame people ſhulde in any wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe abſtayne frome eatynge of the meates offered to ymages / and that for the weake perſones ſake / to whome full knowlege of ſuche maner thynges was natte yet gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Therfore he bade the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyans
<pb facs="tcp:3827:22"/> to confyrme &amp; fortifye this doctryne withe the auctoritye of their dede / &amp; to refrayne / nat only from eatynge of the fleſſhe offered vp in ſacrifyce to ydoles and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / but alſo from all maner thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that might appere euyll / or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye maner waye myght offende weake perſones.</p>
            <p>For albeit he gaue them leaue to eate all maner fleſſhe:<note place="margin">1 Cor 9</note> euen that alſo which was offred to ymages / if it were ſolde in the fleſſhe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket: yet in the churches where they were offred vp to images / he wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in no wyſe graunte them lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye to eate ſuche meates.</p>
            <p>Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lykewyſe do we iuge / that it is to be thought of images (whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che likewyſe / as peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſome man maye haue at home within his owne houſe / ſo that it be done without offendyng of his neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure:
<pb facs="tcp:3827:23"/> euen ſo the vſe of theym in churches or in other places / wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyther they maye be worſhypped or offende and hurte their neybou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in no wyſe longer to be ſuffred.<note place="margin">1 Cor 8</note> ¶ Paule doutles had leuer neuer to haue eaten fleſſhe in all his lyfe than to gyue his brother occaſyon to be offended. And ſhall we all ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reles wynke at ſo many occaſyons bothe of offencyons and alſo of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry?<note place="margin">Mat. 5</note> If Chriſte doth byd the eye to be plucked oute of the heed / which is an obſtacle / and impedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to vs. Howe moch more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought pictures and ymages to be plucked out of churches / by which we do nat only offende weke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons / but alſo do ſet forthe our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyon to be ſcorned &amp; euyll ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of amonge the Turkes and iewes which do conuynce vs / that in this behalfe we do agaynſt the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:23"/> princypall poyntes of the chriſten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayth. Wold god that with this ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſticyon and vayne honouryng of images / we dyd nat ſtoppe and kepe awaye a great meny / both of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Iewes and alſo of the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / from receyuynge and takyng of the chriſten fayth vpon them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>
               </label> Nowe if any man wyll obiecte that for the abuſe (which peraduen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture no man wyll denye) ymages ar nat altogyther to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away (for elles the ſupper of the lorde / &amp; baptyſme / with many other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche are encombred with dyuers abuſes / ought alſo in lyke maner to be abrogated and taken away) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Suliciō. </seg>
               </label> This anſwere do we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto him: That chriſten men ſhulde nat wynke at any abuſe / &amp; therefore whatſoeuer is brought into the churche / contrary to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture / it is to be amended / and to be
<pb facs="tcp:3827:24"/> tryed by the ſquyer &amp; rule of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde / if any thynge do nat a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre with it / it is to be cutte away<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with all the ſpede that may be. and onely that thynge whiche is righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and which is holeſom / is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his owne place / and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in his owne place ſpecyally in the ſouper of the lorde / in baptym and other thynges alſo / which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ben inſtytuted by the lorde.</p>
            <p>But images ar vtterly to be taken away / nat only for the abuſes / but moche more for the worde of god / to the whiche they are playne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and repugnaunte. For we can nat ymagen any maner vtilite whiche may be ſayd to haue come by the reaſon of ymages. On the other ſyde / that the ſuperſticyon of ymages dothe drawe with it an heape of all euylles / we haue heretofore declared.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:24"/>
            <p>¶ To make ſhorte / god neuer for bad any of theſe thynges / wherof any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte or profyte might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſe: but rather what ſoeuer thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is profytable &amp; may make vs bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / he taught full largely as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth Paule very euydently.</p>
            <p>¶ But if any folyſſhe wyſe man doth thynke that images ar there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nat to be taken away / bycauſe he fereth that thoſe weke perſones which nowe ſuꝑſticyouſly do wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippe images / wolde be offended with the puttynge downe of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:<note place="margin">2 Tim 3</note> this man doutles whyles he goth aboute to auoyde frome the ſmoke (as it is ſayde in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe) is fallen into the flamynge fyre. For whyles he fereth to offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de deſperate ꝑſons / with hurtfull offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ymages he holdeth bac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke &amp; hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth better me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which haue begon to ronne the way of the lord
<pb facs="tcp:3827:25"/> without any turnynge agayne. Whoſoeuer doth this ſhalbe gilty of that cryme / of which Paule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth Peter in the epyſtle to the Galatians.<note place="margin">Gala 2</note> For Peter whyles he was afrayde to offende certayne iewes of Ieruſalem at Antioch / &amp; for that cauſe wolde nat vſe the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of eatyng all maner meates as he was wonte to do before: Paule withſtode him to his face i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the whole multitude bycauſe he walked nat the ryght way / according to the truthe of the goſpell. For aſmoch as was i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him with his vnwyſe deſyre to auoyde offendyng of the iewes / he febled the right faithe / &amp; alſo noriſſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incredulyte and vnbelefe of them / whom he ſtudyed to pleaſe in the meane ſeaſon. Brefely he dyd no thynge els / than whyles he went a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute vnwyſely to auoyde one ieo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ꝑdy
<pb facs="tcp:3827:25"/> he did caſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf into twayn. Doutles after this maner to deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to auoyde occaſyons of ſclan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and offenſyons / is the full cauſe of offenſyons. And wolde god it wer nat of ſo gret ſtrength as it is amonge very manye men nowe in theſe dayes. For a man ſhall ſe very many / which bicauſe they wolde imagyne ſome honeſt cloke and colour of their vnbelefe do fayne them ſelues bothe to do &amp; alſo to eſchew very many thinges leſt they might gyue any man oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon to be offended / whan in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede they do it rather to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe of Chriſt from themſelues. For w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this fayned deſyre to wyn certayne curable ꝑſons / they ſhifte well for themſelues / that they may neither haue the euyll wyll of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate perſons / neyther any diſple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſure or hurt done vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:26"/> ſame. We do nat deny verily / that ſuche maner of doctryne and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge is moſt to be enbraced and folowed / whiche is an obſtacle or lettynge to no man / whiche doth purpoſely angre no man / whiche doth turne no mans mynde away from the truthe: yet neuertheleſſe great dilygence ought to be giuen in the meane ſeaſon / that none of thoſe thyngꝭ be let of and omytted wherby the glorye of god and the helth of our neyghtbours / may be furthered and encreaſed. <q>Chriſte him ſelfe is the ſtomblynge ſtone vnto the vnbeleuers: but he is a precyouſe ſtone / vnto them which are fore ordeyned to lyfe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Pe. 2</note>After y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we our ſelues do know the wyll &amp; pleaſure of the lorde / we muſt dilygently labour that other men alſo may lyke and prayſe the ſame. &amp; that other men alſo maye
<pb facs="tcp:3827:26"/> haue luſte &amp; pleaſure to confyrme them ſelues vnto the ſame. If we can nat obteyne this / than oughte we rather to forſake father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / &amp; all our goodes: yea / more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer to renounce our owne ſelues than to reſyſt or gruge againſt the wyll &amp; pleaſure of god. But moſt come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly we ſe it come to paſſe / that a great parte of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had leuer both to get / to maynteyne &amp; kepe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of men with the minyſſhing of goddes honour: Albeit / yet it were better to wyn both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauour of god &amp; alſo of men / with honeſt maners &amp; honeſt lyuynge / &amp; with redy deſyre &amp; wyl to do good vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / if we wold begyn this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wynnynge the fauour of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in other thinges wold lyue in this worlde fauteleſſe / as nere as we coulde / doutleſſe there ſhulde be no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo parcyall in iugement
<pb facs="tcp:3827:27"/> but he wolde by and by gather in mynde / that he wolde neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly nor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out good cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe done of vs / that we haue banyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed pictures and ymages cleane out of churches. But wherto ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de we make many wordes / ſyth it is euydent ynough nowe / that y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages do diminyſſhe the true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of god / and that it is nat poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble / but that weke men be gretly offended / and do take moch hurte by them. For they (I meane weke perſons) wolde paſſe lytell vpon the takynge awaye of ymages / if they wer taught playnly for what conſyderation and ſkyll they were taken awaye. On the other ſyde if they be nat taken awaye / forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they conceyue an opinion / as though it were nat laufull to put them away. Nowe after obſtinate and vncurable perſons / nat onely
<pb facs="tcp:3827:27"/> we can nat with permyttyng / and wynkyng at images / bringe them to goodneſſe: but alſo with oure ſufferaunce and ſlackneſſe we ſhal confyrme and eſtablyſſhe them the more in idolatrye.</p>
            <p>Brefely / if thou haſte ſo great deſyre and loue / to wynne many men to thy lorde / ordre thy ſelfe ſo that other men maye in very dede ſee and perceyue experyence and proufe that Chriſt is a lyue in the / and that all thy dedes and ſayngꝭ do breth and ſauour of him. With out doute / if thou wylte ordre thy ſelfe in this wyſe / thou ſhalt cauſe euen wycked men alſo / that they can nat chuſe but at the leaſt wyſe cloſly in their hertꝭ confeſſe (their conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce driuyng them thervnto) that thou waſte nat onely moued / but alſo compelled by the zele of god to put awaye ymages. And
<pb facs="tcp:3827:28"/> though in the meane ſeaſon many thynges be wantynge in vs: yet that natwithſtandynge we ought to be neuertheleſſe dilygent / to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyde that all ſuch maner thynges be put awaye / which ſoeuer ar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the worde of god. Let vs take no thought for any maner thynge which may caſt vs out any maner way of the fauour of men. Let vs go ſtreyght forth and take the nexte waye to fulfyll the rule of a chriſten mannes lyfe: For a true chriſten man / although he doth in many thinges aknowlege him ſelf to be a ſynner (as he is in very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de) yet doth he neither alowe nor excuſe any maner thyng / whiche doth minyſſhe or deface the honor of his lorde and maiſter Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of the abuſe of ymages we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſpoken ſomewhat here tofore. But if anye man do ſomewhat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tely
<pb facs="tcp:3827:28"/> conſydre &amp; way the mater he ſhall perceyue vndoutedly / that imagis ar falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a farre gretter abuſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men / than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge any heathen men. Images haue gyuen anſweres w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs / they haue wept / one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought more holy &amp; of more po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another. One more louely and more gratious than another: a man ſhal fynde ſome / which in a certayne place haue ſhewed forthe their power in worki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of miracles whan they haue ben tranſlated &amp; remoued into another place:<note place="margin">And yet was it ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tan that thus ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gly delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs / with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles for oure hatynge of the truth / &amp; for oure miſbele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, 2 <hi>theſ</hi> 2</note> they haue ceſſed to do the ſame. Of the ymage at Lauretum / and dyuers other: ſyth the matter is knowen well inough / we nede nat to ſaye any thynge at all. And I praye you / how moch richeſſe in the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſeaſon hath this ſuperſtition of ymages gathered togyther / nat
<pb facs="tcp:3827:29"/> withoute plentuouſe occaſyon of ſclanderouſe offences:<note place="margin">wolde god the miracles of the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magis of walſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gham / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torbury / pppeſwi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, &amp; cheſtre, &amp; ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wer well try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bi ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture to ſee what article of our faith they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med.</note> which ſayd ryches / the glotony and pompe of a ſort of vnthrifty idle belyes hath deſtroyed and waſtfully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed. In as moche therfore as true / full and perfyte faith can nat ſuffre ſo great abhomynatyon: and ſyth it can nat be plucked vp by the rotes with the worde alone (for with the goodly and gloriouſe apparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of holyneſſe / and alſo by the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of long cuſtome and contynuance it hath gotten ſo great auctoritye and eſtimatyon to it ſelfe) it is to be put awaye by the dede ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And wherto nedeth it to ſuffre tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thynges amonge Chriſten men whiche as they can nat but engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre euylles oute of nombre: ſo can they cauſe no hope nor lokynge of any maner profyte to come by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto any man / vnleſſe it be to the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:29"/> ydle viciouſe belyes that receyuen the offrynges. It dyd become vs chriſten men moſt of all to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and ſtyred with the worde of god / which doth ſo playnly and ſo expreſly forbyde all maner of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Whatſoeuer is reed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge ymages in the lawe / in the Prophetes / in the Pſalmes / doth moche more iuſtly apperteyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs whiche ar taught by Chriſt / that god is to be worſhipped i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte &amp; truth / and that Chriſte alſo is nat to be worſhipped i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ymages of wood / of ſtone / of ſyluer / or of other metall:<note place="margin">Io. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <note place="margin">Colo. 3</note> but that he is to be worſhypped rather ſyttyng on the right hande of his father / and that all the membres of the ſeyd Chriſt that is to wyt our neybours are to be ſocoured with dedes of charite.</p>
            <p>And theſe fewe thinges amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge many / it hath lyked vs to borowe
<pb facs="tcp:3827:30"/> of the ſcryptures agaynſt pictures &amp; images / which ſcrypture alone / a chriſten hathe regarded vnto / as vnto the ſhote ankre in all thinges both which ar to be deſyred / &amp; alſo which ar to be eſchewed. But yet bycauſe it can nat be but pleaſure and conforte to the ſame Chriſten man / whatſoeuer eyther doctryne or examples he ſhall fynde in the ſayntes of god / which is conſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and agreynge to the ſcryptures.<note place="margin">Nat in ſaites of the Buſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops of Romes makyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> canoni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynge.</note> We haue thought it expedyente to bringe forth a fewe thynges of the writyngꝭ of the fathers / by which the godly reder ſhall eaſely percey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue that the apoſtles / martyrs / and all the beſt lerned &amp; moſt auncyent fathers taughte the ſame thynge / which is ordeyned &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the word of god / vntyll ſuch tyme as by the Gothyans &amp; the Vanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyans / the chryſten faythe and the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:30"/> more pure knowlege of the truthe began to be gretly minyſſhed and brought in dekay. For in the tyme of ſaynte Hierome / and certayne yeres after him / we doo nat rede / that anye byſſhop beynge of wyſe iugement / dyd ſuffre pictures or images in the churches of chriſten men. Of the which thyng Epipha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius<note place="margin">Epipha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius.</note> / the mooſt holy byſſhoppe of Salamine / in the yle of Cyprus / ſheweth an euident example in his epyſtle to Iohan the byſſhoppe of Hieruſalem / which epyſtle ſaynte Hierome tranſlated into Latyne. For this he writeth: Whan we went togyther to the holye place / which is called Bethell / to make a collectyon there for poore people with the / accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to the cuſtome and maner of the churche: and I was come vnto the vyllage which is called Anablatha / &amp; as I paſſed
<pb facs="tcp:3827:31"/> by dyd ſee a burnynge lampe / and I had aſked what place it was / &amp; had lerned that it was a churche / and had entred into it to praye. I dyd fynde there a vayle hangynge in the churche dores / coloured and paynted / &amp; hauyng as it were the image of Chriſt / or of ſome ſaynt (for I do nat well remembre who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ymage it was) I ſaye / whan I had ſene that in the church of chriſt there dyd hange the ymage of a man / agaynſt the auctoritie of the ſcryptures.<note place="margin">It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re any y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to be in the churche.</note> I dyd cutte it / &amp; gaue counſel to the kepers of that place that they ſhuld rather wynde ſom poore man that were deed / &amp; bury him in it. And they agayne grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge / ſayde by me: If he hadde mynded to cutte it / it was reaſon and right that he ſhuld gyue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vayle and change this: which thynge whan I had herde / I pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed
<pb facs="tcp:3827:31"/> that I wolde gyue one / and ſende it forthwith. Howbeit I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the ſendynge of it ſomwhat the longer / by the reaſon that I entended for to ſende a very good vayle in the ſted of it. &amp; I thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhulde haue had one ſent vnto me oute of Ciprus. Now I haue ſent ſuche one as I coulde gette / &amp; I pray you that you wyll byd the preſtes of the ſame place to receiue this vayle of the bringer whiche we haue ſent / &amp; afterwardꝭ to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde that no mo ſuche maner vayles / which are contrary to our relygion / be hangen vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Lo / here the ſentence of the moſt vertuous biſſhoppe / in whiche he gyueth iugement / by expreſſe and playne wordes / that it is agaynſt ſcripture &amp; oure relygion / that y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of chriſt ar had in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:3827:32"/> of chriſten men / whereof we may gather euidently that in this mater / bothe Ierome &amp; alſo other biſſhops were of the ſame mynde that Epiphanius was of. Herfore Euſebius<note place="margin">Euſebiꝰ</note> alſo reherſeeh / as a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge &amp; an vnwonte thing / that in Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarea Philippe (in which cyte the woman was borne / whom Chriſt healed from the fluxe of blode) He dyd ſee two images of braſſe / the one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman / thother of chriſt our ſauyour / whiche ymages yet were ſet vp at churche dores / nat in the churche ſelfe / as the ſame Euſebius recordeth.<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.</note> And at the laſt he ſayth thus: It is no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle if thoſe perſones of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles which dyd beleue / were ſene for ſuche benefytes as they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the ſauyour / to offre / as you wolde ſaye / ſuche a maner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde or recompence / ſyth it is ſo
<pb facs="tcp:3827:32"/> that we do ſee ymages &amp; tables of the apoſtles Peter &amp; Paule / &amp; alſo of Chriſt our ſauyour to be karue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and paynted: euen theſe dates alſo We haue ſene moreouer olde yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of them kepte of certayne per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones / which thynge me thinke is obſerued / accordyng to the cuſtom of the gentyles without any dyffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence / bycauſe they ar wont in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wyſe to honoure them / whom they thought worthye of honoure.<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge &amp; honori<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, cam fyrſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles to the iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / and ſo vnto vs.</note> For that the armes or ymages of olde men are reſerued and kepte for a remembraunce to theym that ſhall come after: it is a ſygne and token both of theyr honoure / and alſo of thoſe mennes loue towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des them.<note place="margin">The vii. boke the xiiii. ca.</note> Thus ſayth Euſebius in the eccleſyaſticall hiſtorie.</p>
            <p>Hereof we do eaſely perceyue / that the ymages which Euſebius dyd ſe / were ſet vp / nat within the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:33"/> churches / but at the church dores.</p>
            <p>Agayne / nat to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cent that they ſhulde be honored / but rather that they ſhulde be a teſtimony &amp; recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de howe great &amp; valiaunt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme / &amp; therfore worthy to be had in ꝑpetuall memorie / who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ymages were reſerued &amp; kepte: All whiche thynges neuertheleſſe Euſebius dothe not hyde / to haue taken their begynning of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles &amp; heathen people. But what thynke ye that he wolde haue ſayd if he hadde ſeen ymages ſet vp in churches / and no leſſe worſhyped of chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer they were of any gentyles / whiche thynge (a lacke for petye) it is vndoubted both than to haue be done: yea / &amp; to be done euen now i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe dayes alſo. Of theſe thynges therfore we may gather what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe / why the old fathers dyd write nothyng
<pb facs="tcp:3827:33"/> agaynſt ſuche maner of images: for there was no man at that tyme whiche dyd ſo moche as ones dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / that euer ſo gret a multytude of images ſhulde crepe into chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as hath cropen in: for aſmoch as they knowe it to be forbydden with ſo open and euydent wordes of god / and playne teſtimonyes of the ſcrypture. But agaynſt the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the gentyles / a man ſhal fynde many thinges writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the fathers / very connyngly and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently / bycauſe the ſuperſticyon of theym dyd reygne euerywhere euen at the ſame tyme / in whiche thoſe holy men were lyuynge. yea and was defended of the gentyles with the ſame wepens / with whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che both in oure tyme / and alſo in the tyme of our fathers / certayne chriſten men haue gone aboute to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; maynteyn their images.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage is</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3827:34"/> What ſo euer thynge Lactancius<note place="margin">Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ꝰ</note> wrot againſt the idoles &amp; images of the gentyles / we maye by very good right apply the ſame agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte our images: albeit in his tyme (as we haue ſayde) they were nat yet vſed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge criſten men. Amonge many places it lyketh me at this tyme to allege one: for thus he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth of the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyls:<note place="margin">Libro. ii. ca. iii.</note> If you do therfore fere &amp; worſhip yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des by ſuche images / bycauſe you do iuge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in heuen: why do you nat than lyfte vp your eyes in to heuen? why do you rather loke to walles / to ſtockes &amp; ſtones / than to that place where you do beleue that they be? This ſame queſtion in lyke maner may we demaunde of our ſuperſticyouſe chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men: If they do beleue that god &amp; ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are in heuen / why do they nat rather lyfte vp theire eyes to that
<pb facs="tcp:3827:34"/> place / than to the deed ymages? But let vs here alſo Athanaſe<note place="margin">Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note> / wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng in this wyſe agaynſt the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles.<note place="margin">It is im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſyble that any image ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſente either ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deꝑted: for the bodye is erth, and the ſoule is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented bi any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terme y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. wherfor Paule ſaith / we knowe that wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atſoeur ymage is in this world / it is a vain thing no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g nothing ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng.</note> Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay (I beſech you) howe or after what maner god is knowen by images / whether is it by the mater &amp; ſtuffe put rounde a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout them: orels is it by the ſhape and facyon brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſtuffe? If it be by the ſtuffe of the images that he is knowen / than what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth any ſhape or facion to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught in by the workeman? &amp; why is nat god ſhewed and knowen as well by al maner of ſtuffe before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any images be made / ſyth all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges do witnes &amp; declare his glori? But if the ſhape &amp; facyon brought in to the ſtuffe be the cauſe of the knowlege of god: what nedeth than any payntynge or any other ſtuffe at all? and why is natte god knowen rather by the very lyuely
<pb facs="tcp:3827:35"/> creature / whoſe ſhapes or ymagꝭ be ſo perfectly knowen? for dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of god ſhuld be more clerely and euydently knowen / if it were ſhewed by the lyuely crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures both reaſonable &amp; vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable / than by the deed and vnmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable creatures.<note place="margin">God is knowen ſayth Paule. Ro. i. by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this worlde.</note> Therfore whan you do graue or paynte ymages / for the entent to haue vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and knowlege of god: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth you do an vnworthy &amp; an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mete thynge. &amp;c. Nowe Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius wolde neuer haue purpoſed in his mynde / to write any ſuche maner thynge agaynſt the genty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / if he had ſene the chriſten men of his tyme entangled &amp; wrapped in ſuch ſuperſtityon of images / as we do ſee a gret parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde to be pytuouſely ſnarled nowe in our tyme: but he wolde rather ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue exerciſed his penne againſt chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten
<pb facs="tcp:3827:35"/> men / if they had ben lyke our chriſten men nowe a dayes. But nothynge letteth / but that we may very accordingly applye the ſame thynge againſt our ſuperſticyous chriſten men: For they pretende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cauſe of hauynge ymages / with the which Athanaſius reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that the gentyles were moued that is to wit / that by images they maye be put in remembraunce of god: which thynge ſyth the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of god (whether we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydre the ſtuffe or the ſhape / and fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) may do it moche more effectually (as Athanaſius iugeth full well) there is no nede that we ſhulde ronne vnto the workes of men / which do repreſent but onely I wote nat what falſe and vayne image vnto vs. For whom ſoeuer trees / ſtones / ſyluer / golde / &amp; other ſtuffe / wherof images are made:
<pb facs="tcp:3827:36"/> fynally whom the ſyght of man / to whom god hath giuen lyfe &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can natte ſtyre nor put in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of god: ſurely images ſhal natte ſtyre vp that man with anye frute or profyte: for they (as Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen writeth agaynſte Selſus) do rather plucke away the memori &amp; mynde of man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god / &amp; do turne the eyes of the mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de bacwardes / to behold &amp; conſydre erthly thinges. For euery man knoweth / that the more nere that one thynge reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth another in nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie / ſo moche the more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it doth renew the remembraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce in vs of that thynge / to whom it is lyke. For trees or ſtones do more ſurely and lyuely putte vs in remembraunce of god / whan they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered of vs / hauyng their owne naturall ſhape &amp; facyon / ſo as they were fyrſt created of god:
<pb facs="tcp:3827:36"/> than whan by the worke and craft of men beynge beryued of theire owne naturall ſhape / they doo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe &amp; reſemble vnto vs the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and lykeneſſe of man / or of any other thynge. For ſoner ſhall the remembraunce come to thy mynde of the Karuer or Paynter / whoſe workmanſhip thou doſt merueyle at / than the remembrance of god / the creatour &amp; maker of all thingꝭ. It is therefore nothynge els but a pure diſceyte of the deuyll / which calleth vs from the praiſynge and charitable louynge of the lyuely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of god / vnto deed ymages of wood or ſtone / which ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a folyſſhe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaiter of god / hath folyſſhly karuen or paynted. We coulde alſo allege many other te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtymonyes oute of the writynges of the fathers: but it ſhulde be all in vayne / to recyte any mo to him
<pb facs="tcp:3827:37"/> whiche is natte moued with theſe which we haue alredy reherſed.</p>
            <p>Here we haue thought it verye expedient and neceſſary to declare and make playne / according to the truthe of hyſtories / whan and by what begynners images began to come vp amonge chriſten men: &amp; who againe on the other ſyde did their endeuoure to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe and with howe moche buſyneſſe / and howe great ieoperdy / good &amp; well dyſpoſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue attempted this thinge / vntyl the church was brought into this preſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition and ſtate of thynges fallynge inceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſantly to worſe &amp; worſe.<note place="margin">Very y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delnes / &amp; ydle ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glygence of Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuffred firſt this idolatry of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping images <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o entre in to the churche / and their gredye &amp; inſacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes holdeth yet ſtylle this ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye.</note> Vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly the lawes / aſwell of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten emperours / as of the chriſten counſels / made agaynſte images / came than firſt forth / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through the ſlouthfulneſſe &amp; neglygence of byſſhops / &amp; their vayne curyouſe
<pb facs="tcp:3827:37"/> deſyres to wyn the fauour of god / nat only images &amp; pictures crepte into the churches / but alſo (which is wonte comenly to chaunce) they began to be worſhipped of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. We rede that Serenus / the byſſhop of Maſſilia<note place="margin">Serenꝰ byſſhop of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia.</note> / a very holy man / was ſo diſpleaſed / &amp; toke it ſo greuouſely (as reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was) that images were ſette vp in churches: that he dyd caſt downe all the ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges atones which wer in his chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che: did breke them / and at the laſt dyd alſo burne theym. We do nat deny / but that this dede of Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus was ſore rebuked of Gregory which was called Gregorius ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus<note place="margin">Gregori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus.</note> / and that the ſeyd Serenus was admonyſſhed &amp; counſelled of the ſayd Gregorye<note place="margin">Gret gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan firſt to teache his floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with theſe bil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de bokes</note> / that he ſhulde nat forbyd or let images to be had but that he ſhulde teche the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of them in any wyſe to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded.
<pb facs="tcp:3827:38"/> But what other thynge ſhuld the ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derdberer of relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vertue fallyng in decay / do in this mater / as well as in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?<note place="margin">By this maner of doctrine, mai yei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge what a ſhepard this gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at doctor was.</note> For about y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme the church of Rome began to threten / ꝓnoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate &amp; giue lykelyhod of gret ruyn of the faith afterwardꝭ to folowe.</p>
            <p>But amonge the Grekes / Leo<note place="margin">Leo Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure of the Grekes.</note> themperour / the .iii. of that name a man both well lerned / &amp; alſo ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous &amp; godly (he raygned in the yere of our lorde .vii.C.lxxxiiii) diſtroyed all images vniuerſally / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded Gregorie the .iii.<note place="margin">here may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſmell what a ſheperde Gregory the third was.</note> of that name by his letters / that he ſhuld do the ſame thinge lykewiſe at Rome. But this Gregorie nat onely refuſed to be obedyent to the emperours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / <note place="margin">Before he wolde nat haue them ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nored, &amp; nowe in deſpite of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure he decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be in high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> but alſo at Rauenna was the authour &amp; be gynner of ſedition / to which cytie he called a certayne meyny of byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes
<pb facs="tcp:3827:38"/> &amp; made a counſel / in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he decreed agaynſte thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement / that images ought to be had in moche more ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure than euer they were before.</p>
            <p>And to the entent that he might the moore boldely inſtytute thys thynge agaynſt themperour with oute any punyſſhement:<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the v.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Here the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure called a counſell without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome / yea, &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rected the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer erro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niꝰ &amp; ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matike counſell of the biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome bi the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures,</note> nat very longe before / he had gone aboute traitourouſly to forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour and to fall vnto the part of the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che kynge. After the deth of Leo / Conſtantyne his ſonne / the fyfth of that name / wyllyng to conferme his fathers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; decree / called togyther all the lerned men and byſſhoppes oute of all Grece lande / beyng in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre. CCC.xxx. which comparynge the ſcriptures to the reaſons of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell / which we ſpake of before / called by Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gori: determyned with one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:3827:39"/> That it is nat laufull to them whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che by Chriſt do beleue in god / to haue any images either of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atoure or the creatures to honour them: but rather of the ieoperdyes of offenſyons or hurtes that they were all to be taken away atones So that from the begynnynge of Leo / Conſtantyne his ſonne / and all his ſucceſſours dyd cleue to / &amp; abyde by it / vntyll ſuche tyme that the cruell woman Hirene<note place="margin">Hiren.</note> went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that horryble and excedynge wycked tragedy / wherof we ſhall ſpeke nat longe herafter. But the decrees of that wycked woman / were vertuouſely abrogated and ſuppreſſed by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantins ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the ſyxte of that name. There cometh nowe happely to my mynde / the decree of Theodoſius<note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſius.</note> &amp; Valens<note place="margin">Valens.</note> / which Petrus Crinitꝰ<note place="margin">Petrus Crinitꝰ.</note> / a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had red many thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / doth recyte
<pb facs="tcp:3827:39"/> in the nynth boke / De honeſta diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina: his owne verye wordes. I ſhall faythfully &amp; truly reherſe:</p>
            <p>Valens &amp; Theodoſius<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Theodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſius and Valens.</note> the noble emperours wrot to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> officer called Prefectus pretorius: Foraſmoche as our dilygent ſtudy &amp; care is / in all thingꝭ to maynteyne &amp; vphold the faith &amp; honour of god: we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byd any maner ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to graue or ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the image of chriſt our ſauyour of ſtone / of wood / or of any other ſtuffe / or els to paynte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame with colours. yea / and wherſoeuer any ſuch image be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that it be taken awaye / and they ſore punyſſhed / who ſoeuer ſhall attempte any thynge contrarye to our decrees and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement / in whiche thynge if any man doo requyre an authour / let him rede the decrees and commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Emperours / whiche haue
<pb facs="tcp:3827:40"/> ben collected and gathered by a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre of the righte connynge men / Tribunianus / Baſylydes / Theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>philus / Diſcorus / and other / at the commaundement of the mooſt noble Emperour Iuſtinian.</p>
            <p>Thus farre ſayth Crinitus.</p>
            <p>It is therfore euydent and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt / that themperours alſo whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che were before the tyme of Leo / dydde dilygentlye prouyde / that the ſuperſticyon of Images ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de nat by any maner meanes pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and defyle the churches of cry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men. The fyrſt of all other (as farre as we can gather of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories) which dyd cauſe Images to be paynted in churches: Was Pontius Paulinus byſſhoppe of Nola<note place="margin">Pontiꝰ paulinꝰ byſſhop of Nola the fyrſte cauſer that ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges wer paynted.</note> / about the yere of our lorde ccccl. For he ſolemniſynge yerely the byrth daye of ſaynt Felix / was wonte to make a great and a coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3827:40"/> feſt vnto the churche / &amp; to then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that thei which ſate at the ſeid feſt / ſhulde be the ſoner and more eaſely prouoked to temperaunce / &amp; to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderatyon of godly thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: he paynted on the churche walles / ymages of the hiſtories of the olde teſtament / that they ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue ſomwhat alſo wherewith they mighte fede and delyte theire eyes frutefully. Afore this Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus you ſhall nat lyghtly fynde that any ſuch thinges was attemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by any man / at the leaſtwyſe / beyng of any famouſe memorie. For in ſuche wyſe by lytell and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell / this ſuperſticyon muſt nedes crepe in: lykewyſe as other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges did / which haue corrupted the puryte &amp; prefection of the churche. Nowe who is he / that dothe nat perceyue and ſee / that Paulinus dyd two maner waies offende? for
<pb facs="tcp:3827:41"/> fyrſt agaynſte the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of ſaynte Paule / he was bolde / &amp; toke vpon him ſelfe to make open feſtes in the churche. And (which agayne was as greate an offence / and ſuche as can nat be excluded) he begane with images to exhorte men vnto the loue &amp; exerciſynge of temperaunce / whan he beynge a chriſten man / ought rather to haue gone aboute to do the ſame / with holeſom doctryne &amp; good example Wherfore it doth euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly appere that this byſſhop dyd in no wyſe begyn that thynge of a pure godly ſpirit: but if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll do well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydre &amp; way euerythynge / he ſhall fynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the ſame ſpirite / that is to wytte / moſt recheles &amp; diſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of godly thynges: other men alſo haue taken vpon them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ymages. For the popes &amp; biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (I wotte nat whether tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe
<pb facs="tcp:3827:41"/> euyll wyll / or els thorowe a certayne pride) began with tothe and nayle to defende the vſe / or ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the abuſe of ymages againſt the Greke emperours: vntyll ſuch tyme as by the labour and helpe of Hyrenes<note place="margin">Hirene Em<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſſe.</note> (which after the deceaſſe of Leo her huſbande / had the rule and gouernance of thempyer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres) a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell was aſſembled at Nice<note place="margin">Here mai ye ſe what ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le this wycked woman bare in the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of Nece.</note> / in which counſell ſhe cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to be abrogated &amp; dyſadnulled whatſoeuer was before decreed bi Conſtantyne / concernyng the put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge awaye of images. Neither coulde this wyckedneſſe ſuffyce &amp; content her mynde: but ſhe did cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the bodye of Conſtantyne to be digged vp againe out of the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to be brent to aſſhes / and laſt of all to be throwen into the ſee.</p>
            <p>This very ſame Hyrene / after that ſhe was by her ſonne depoſed
<pb facs="tcp:3827:42"/> from her tyrannouſe empery / lefte nothynge vnaſſayed nor neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vntyll by abhominable &amp; tray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torous craftes ſhe wan againe the empier vnto her ſelfe: which thing whan ſhe had brought to paſſe / ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to her owne mynde / ſhe dyd caſt her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne into priſon / pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked oute his eyes / &amp; in concluſyon ſlewe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo.<note place="margin">here mai ye ſee by what a wycked Byſſhop of Rome conſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a wicked woman / the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery was craftely tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d from the Grekes to the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che men.</note> But whan ſhe fered that her tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ſhuld nat continue nor laſt longe / ſhe made labours (the pope of Rome beynge broker and ſpokeſman) to be maried vnto Charles the gret / otherwiſe called Charlemayne / kyng of Fraunce: and for this cauſe ſhe gaue lycence to the byſſhop of Rome to tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the crowne of thempier of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto Charles / hopynge verily that her owne tyrannye ſhulde be ſafe / if by tranſlatyng thempier of the Grekes traytorouſely vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:42"/> Frenchemen / ſhe dyd bynde / nat only Charles / but alſo the biſſhop of Rome: and make them her fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des with this great benefyte.</p>
            <p>But whan Nicephorus<note place="margin">Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus.</note> / which than was capitaine of the army of the Grekes perceyued theſe trayto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rouſe diſceytes / forthewith in all haſt he dyd caſt Hirene into priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as ſhe had diſcerued / in which ſhe made a wretched ende / &amp; changed this lyfe with deth / worthy &amp; mete for ſuche goodlye actes as ſhe had done.<note place="margin">O cruell woman,</note> This ſame Hyrene whiche dygged vp the deed bodye of her father in lawe and brent it. Which put out her owne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes eyes / and ſlewe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in priſon: which betraied themperour of the Grekes: &amp; this ſame byſſhop of Rome / the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and helper of the moſt wicked and vngracyouſe womans purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes &amp; enforceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: which biſſhop
<pb facs="tcp:3827:43"/> toke awaye from the right &amp; lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full emperoure his empyer / &amp; dyd put in another i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the empier who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſed him ſelfe: but yet vpon this condicyon / that he hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue Rome and Italye for his parte: This worſhipfull couple (I ſay) aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced imagꝭ vnto this eſtimatyon &amp; honour. For whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer imagꝭ or pictures ar i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: they maye nat without good cauſe thanke theſe two: for it / as their fyrſt beginners / howbeit the ſucceſſours alſo of Charles / dyd afterwardes their dilygent ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure to maynteyne and vpholde theſe abhominatyons: leſt the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation and ground worke of idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trye which charles had layde / ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de haue lacked buyldynge to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe it full of all impyetie and wyckedneſſe. Howbeit theſe men in tymes paſſed / dyd neuer than
<pb facs="tcp:3827:43"/> pollute and defyle temples &amp; chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with ſo many images / &amp; ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge ſo manyfeſt apparance of idolatry (whiche thynge we maye perceyue and ſee euen yet by thoſe whiche they buylde) as haue ben ſette vp euerywhere in theſe laſte v. hundreth yeres / to the occaſyon of moſt vayne honour: which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to thentent to make it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more accepted with falſe and lyeng won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders / he ſtyred vp &amp; moued ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticyouſe perſones in euery place / to begynne pylgrymages to ſuche images to their great hynderance both of god / of fayth / and of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe. For (I praye you) tell me what other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſhal a man fynde in ſuch maner churches of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed virgin: than certayne fylthye and ſmoky images? for god (ſuch is his excedynge goodneſſe) leſt any occaſyon of ydolatrye ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:3827:44"/> be lefte vnto men / he wolde that the body of the bleſſed vyrgin ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de nat be knowen wher it became, Lykewiſe as he did by the body of Moſes.<note place="margin">And yet as noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expres an angel by any ſenſyble images ſo is ther nothyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>depted repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of ſayntes.</note> We wyl ſay nothing here of the ymages of ſaynte Anne / of ſayntes / nor of the images of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: which men with lyke ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticyon haue begon to ſet vp / wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere in euery corner / &amp; to worſhip them. And (which is as gret a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhnes as may be) whan there ar ſo many images ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes in one church: to one they do gyue I wot nat what power of workynge my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles / to the great hynderaunce &amp; contempte of all the reſydue. Bref<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / ſo gret is the vanyte of images that though i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very dede thei could put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of god: yet neuertheleſſe for dyuerſe occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of offencyons and idolatry / it were expedient &amp; neceſſary to haue
<pb facs="tcp:3827:44"/> them taken away in all the haſt / ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordyng to the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Eſechias the moſt holy kyng / which did caſt downe &amp; breke the braſen ſerpent / which was ſet vp by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god: whan he had percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that it was worſhipped con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god.<note place="margin">In the xviii. cha of the iiii. boke of the kinges.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe thinges which we haue hytherto recyted / if he that fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the glori of Chriſt / wyll dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently way &amp; conſydre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his minde he ſhall vndoutedly perceyue / that whatſoeuer ymages ar honoured in churches / or any maner waye maye be honoured / neither ought neyther maye be ſuffred amonge chriſten men / vnleſſe we wyll doo agaynſte the manyfeſt precepte of god / and diſpiſe and ſet at nought both the faythe and alſo the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the apoſtles / martyrs / and of alſo of holye fathers. Fynally
<pb facs="tcp:3827:45"/> excepte we can fynde in our herte in the ſtede of the lawes / whiche haue ben made bothe by Chriſten emperours / &amp; alſo counſels to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the traditions of the biſſhop of Rome / &amp; of the moſt wicked wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man / whoſe delyte &amp; pleaſure both of them was in trayſon / roberyes / and contynuall ſtudye / to deuyde and diſtroye the empyer.</p>
            <p>¶ Fynally as concernynge the ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge downe and puttyng awaye of alters / erecte and dedycate vnto images or ſayntes / they which ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked abuſyons of the maſſe / may &amp; wyll be ſone ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed &amp; contented without any gret buſyneſſe: but they whiche do nat knowe the ſayde abuſes / can nat be lightly pacifyed: vnleſſe thei be fyrſt taught howe gret the abuſes of the maſſe ar in the ſyght of god.</p>
            <p>Therfore this one thyng we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre
<pb facs="tcp:3827:45"/> to be conſydered of them that fere / drede / and loue god / in what maner and for what ende / purpoſe and entent / chriſt our ſauyour did inſtitute his holy ſupper. Truly to thentent that his diſcyples (that is to ſaye / they whiche wyll lyue accordynglye to his doctryne and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente) aſſemblynge to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther / <note place="margin">The ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ꝑ of our lord was come to mani me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at his table / &amp; nat a pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng and drinki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone at the auter</note> ſhulde take that miſticall breed / and miſticall drinke in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men / and eueryone put other in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrance of that incomparable charytie of Chriſte / by whiche he ſuffred deth for their ſaluatyon: &amp; by the reaſon therof / their fayth &amp; truſt in god beyng encreaſed / ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be inflamed both with the hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſynnes / and alſo with loue of all vertues / profeſſynge theym ſelues to be one bodye &amp; one breed in Chriſt.<note place="margin">the firſte of the Cori<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. the x, capi.</note> By this meanes onely holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar nouryſſhed with chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:3827:46"/> the meate of lyfe. Nowe compare vnto theſe thynges / that which is comenly done in maſſes. Maſſes of the popyſſhe preeſtes moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally are done for their owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes ſake: or els at the leſtwyſe to purchaſe ſome meryte afore god / which thynge nat onely declareth the abuſes therof / but alſo that thei thus abuſed ar diſpleſant &amp; abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynable to god. Beſydes this there ar ſaide and done many thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / whiche do turne awaye oure myndes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt which reygneth in heuen / vnto the worke of the preeſt. The congregatyon hereth no doctryne or exhortacyon i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mother tonge / that they might be edifyed therby. There is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon had / althoughe the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des whiche the preeſt reherſeth do make mention of it. And whyles the preeſt alone dothe receyue the
<pb facs="tcp:3827:46"/> breed and the cuppe of the lorde: there is nat celebrated that ſame ſupper that Paule ſpeketh of. for in the fyrſt epyſtle to the Corinth. The .xi. chapiter / he ſpeketh of no priuate ſupper / but of a comen ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of many togyther. There are ſayde alſo many thinges which ar playne repugnant to the ſcripture for they do teache to truſt vnto the merytes and interceſſyon of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And (whiche thinge is mooſt hyghlye to be abhorred) where as the onely one oblatyon of Chriſte (by which only ones done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe / we ar aſſoyled &amp; ſanctifyed for euermore) ought to be preched: the preſt boſteth / that as ofte times as he doth his maſſe / ſo ofte tymes he doth offre Chriſte to his father / and therfore doth by it obteyne the puttynge away of all euyls / and a hepe of all good thynges to them
<pb facs="tcp:3827:47"/> onely / whiche by gyuynge anye thynge to the preeſte / doo make theym ſelues partetakers of the maſſe / by the reaſon whereof it is come to paſſe / that ſo many men / all care of innocency layde a parte do hope that heuen ſhalbe opened vnto them eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſuch maner maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alone. Whoſoeuer recogniſeth and knowlegeth the lorde Ieſus as our onely ſauyour &amp; ſanctifyer. If he do conſyder theſe thynges dilygently / and with the ſame do compare theſe thynges which our lorde both ſayde &amp; dyd / &amp; beſydes that dyd betake to vs for to be rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated and often tymes put in vſe he ſhall eaſely perceyue &amp; ſee / that there was neuer any ſuperſticyon in tymes paſſed / whiche had in it ſelf ſo gret impietye &amp; wickednes / ſo great contempte of god / ſo gret diſtructyon of all vertues / as hath
<pb facs="tcp:3827:47"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deteſtable &amp; abhominable abuſe of the maſſe / ſo as it hath ben abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe certayne yeres. And her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of whan he knoweth / that nothing is ſo moche to be hated and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of chriſten men: he ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue that all remembrance of this abuſe is vtterly to be taken away. And therfore thabuſed alters / the very open ſhoppes of ſo great ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrye / and the ryches of theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyces / euen the pernicyouſe ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe wyues to all chriſten peple no rulers in anye condityon wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge their offyce to be approued only of Chriſt ought in no wyſe to ſuffre them. Let chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know the truthe of the mater / and than afterwardes let them iudge.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all / this thynge alſo is to be obſerued i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this mater / though neuer ſo gret offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyons &amp; occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of euyls come through pictures
<pb facs="tcp:3827:48"/> and Images / <note place="margin">It belon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth to the chefe rulers to reforme theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes.</note> abuſed maſſes / and falſe &amp; vayn worſhyppyng of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / that yet for all that / it is nat laufull for any priuate man / but the heed offycer &amp; ruler to caſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out / namely oute of open &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men places. For in aſmoche as they ar outwarde thynges / no man ought to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him more power ouer theym than the condition and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of euery man ſhall require / that is to wytte / that euery man priuat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly banyſhe theym out of his owne mynde / reiectynge the folyſhe eſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation of them. Nowe to an hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeholder it belongeth / accordynge to thexample of Iames the patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arche<note place="margin">Iames the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triarche.</note> / to clenſe and rydde his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of theym. But to caſte theym out of churches and comen places it is the duetye of the heed offycer and gouerner / which duety (than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be to Chriſte) our gouernour
<pb facs="tcp:3827:48"/> hath knowen / and hath executed with chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grauite. And one thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge it is to be eſchewed in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyneſſe / lykewyſe as in all other / whiche it belongeth to Chryſten mennes charge for to do (and it is the counſell of Saynte Paule) that we do nat ſet forth our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the euyll wordes of men: &amp; that the thynge whiche was inſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted to the helth and ſaluation of many men / be nat an occaſyon of hurte to any man. Wherfore if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man in deſtroyeng of ymages / ſhulde do any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſely outragiouſly / &amp; paſſe the meaſure of charite / he ſhulde bynde hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe by ſo moche to the more greuouſe ſynne / by howmoch the thynge is more holy / in whiche he foloweth his owne ſenſuall luſt / &amp; the officer ought (nat withoute good cauſe)
<pb facs="tcp:3827:49"/> to punyſſhe hi for brekyng of loue and charytie. Alſo it ought nat to be aſcribed to anye ourtragyouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / though vnſenſyble &amp; dombe images be nat ſo ſoftly &amp; ſo tender<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly handled / as certayne men (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a folyſſhe imaginatyon / <note place="margin">Images haue ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; fele nat / eyes &amp; ſee nat, eares &amp; heare nat &amp;c. &amp; yet wyll we ryde and go many a mile to worſhyp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with praier, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>delles, co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / and money.</note> as though w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fygure &amp; ſymilitude of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they had alſo ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wyttes &amp; reaſon) ar wont to haue compaſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / &amp; to ſorowe ſome what whan they ar broken. For if we were diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed to take away images / after ſuch maner &amp; facion as ſcripture te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth / whiche facion doutleſſe muſt nedes be beſt: we oughte to breke them / yea / &amp; that all to powder / that they might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be made whole agayne / nor be reſtored in to ſo wycked an abuſe in whiche we ought nat to haue ſo greatly regarded the laboure and crafte of man / ſyth it is our dutye
<pb facs="tcp:3827:49"/> to offre euen our owne ſelues alſo to the croſſe / &amp; to all maner affly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction / rather than to be wyllynge to gyue occaſyon of fallynge / &amp; of idolatry to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> walketh in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of vertue &amp; godlyneſſe. And wolde god there were in all men aſmoche care &amp; dilygence to make moche of / &amp; to be ware of offendi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or hurting the very lyuely images which god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf hath made to his owne lykeneſſe: as we do ſee to be in very many men / that theſe deed and dombe images ſhulde nat be hardly / nor vnreuerently entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. To conclude / ſhortly to pluck downe images &amp; pictures / and to rid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quyte out of churches is an holye thynge / &amp; ought to be begon accordyng to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of god. It is conuenyent therfore &amp; mete / that it be ꝑformed &amp; fulfylled in ſuche wyſe / that it may be accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:3827:50"/> and alowed of almightye god. That is to wit / that they be ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away / that there be no whit of them remayni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / namely to lyke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe / &amp; alſo yet neuertheles / nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g be done preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſly / nor outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly / nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that may gyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man good cauſe to be troubled but that all thynges be done chary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tably of pure &amp; perfecte loue / &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to do ꝓfyte to all men. &amp; after this facyon god grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be delyuered from idols &amp; images through the whole world fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one ende to thother. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>¶ The tranſlatoure of this lytell treatyſe oute of Latyne into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſſhe to the indyfferent reder.</head>
            <p>SYth it is chaunſed vnto me (good indyfferent reder) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that happeneth / &amp; aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:3827:50"/> euery man / whiche of a good zele endeuoureth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf to ꝓmoue / further / &amp; ſet forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel / to the honour &amp; glorie of god / &amp; edifye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of his churche / beit by ſyncere and true prechynge or otherwyſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatyng or compylyng of any / beit neuer ſo frutefull a treatyſe / euen to be myſtaken and myſreported. And yet I dyd but only the offyce of a faithful tranſlatour / interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng the wordes &amp; ſentences of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which did fyrſt make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che authours ſyth they be of no les leenynge than iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; ſo many gathered togyther in one conſente confyrmed with ſcryptures euery where / &amp; by their aduerſaryes yet neuer impugned ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed / &amp; the boke both in latin &amp; alſo in Duch frely red &amp; ſolde by the ſpace of .v. yeres nowe fully paſſed in euery churche where the execrable rytes
<pb facs="tcp:3827:51"/> and tradicyons of the byſſhop of Rome be expulſed &amp; put out / &amp; the goſpell brought in purely &amp; ſynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to be preached. I thoughte it might well &amp; worthely be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. yea / &amp; ſo moche the more was I animated &amp; encouraged the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to do: bycauſe I dyd here our cheife preachers / men nat onely of good learnynge &amp; pure iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / but alſo of eſtimation &amp; auctoritie in their ſermons dayly preach fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agaynſt the ſame abuſes &amp; vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly condempne them. And if an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyfferent reder with iudgement / wolde conferre the places / &amp; expen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the mynde of the authours / he ſhulde ſee theym ſpeke / neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the maſſe / ne yet agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the bleſſed ſacrament that Chriſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuted: but onely againſt the abuſe of the maſſe / &amp; ſacrament brought in of the byſſhop of Rome / &amp; his
<pb facs="tcp:3827:51"/> adherentes / to ſatiſfye their inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable belyes / to fede their auarice and to ſupporte &amp; maynteyne their falſe vſurped dignyte and power. Neuertheles to ſatiſfye ſome men I am nowe compelled agayne to printe this lytell treatyſe defenſed with this buckler / that is to ſaye / that wher they reporte me to haue diſpyſed the maſſe or the ſupper of the lorde as ſcripture calleth it / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whiche thynge (I take god to wytneſſe) I thought nothing leſſe but I ſay to them &amp; afferme it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly / that I do but onely ſpeke agaynſt the abuſes thereof / &amp; that maſſe onely is there ſpoken of (as euery reaſonable man may ꝑceiue and ſee) which is inſtytuted &amp; abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the byſſhops of Rome / their popyſſhe complyces / and counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours / which they bye &amp; ſel as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das dyd / &amp; offre vp Chriſt agayne
<pb facs="tcp:3827:52"/> for money / whan it ſtandeth playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the .ix. chap. to the Hebrues / that Chriſt therfore is nat entred into heuen bycauſe that he wolde many tymes &amp; often offre vp hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf for ſo muſt he haue oftentymes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered / from the tyme that he went vp. But he ſuffred but ones: yea / &amp; that nowe in the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. Wherefore he muſt be but ones of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred vp / which to conferme yet mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re certaynly / he addeth in the next chap. theſe wordes: Vnica enim oblatione. &amp;c. That is to ſaye: by onely one oblacyon he hath effectu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſely for euermore made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect / which ar his holy elect / agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt which abuſes only that place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later ende of this lytell treatiſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth / which maner of maſſes thus bought &amp; ſolde / and in the whiche they ſo oft for money offre vp criſt crucifyenge him agayne: it were
<pb facs="tcp:3827:52"/> better that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> than dayly thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> holye a ſacrame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> holyer entent inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and executed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> mityue churche / in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> appoſtles / wherfore I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by a fewe moo wordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that place / that ſo hathe ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome men more playnly expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and declared the myndes of the authours. So that frome henſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I truſt no man wyll be offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded with this lytell treatyſe / but onely they / in whoſe breſtes the popyſſhe tradicyons do yet ſtycke faſt / whoſe conſcyences ar yet mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked with his whote yron / and out of whoſe hertes his abuſes are ſo loth to be extirped and drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out. But god almighty whiche of his mercyfull goodneſſe of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly maketh a rightwyſe man / and
<pb facs="tcp:3827:53"/> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oure of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e farue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> breth his holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the hertes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they maye rede all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> better iudgemente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to their owne edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wlege and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynge of the truth of goddes worde.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed for W. Marſhall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3827:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
